[{"question":"<p><strong>______ is the term that describes the cost of one product in terms of forgone<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p><strong>production\/acquisition of others.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Marginal cost","Production\/acquisition cost","Optimum cost","Opportunity cost"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>An activity does not have a cost when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The activity does not require the giving up of any other activity or thing","The government pays for it","It is carried out by a non- governmental organisation","It is not priced"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choices arise on account of _________<\/strong><\/p>","options":["(A) numerous wants","Enough money to undertake effective demand","Scale of preference","Human wants being numerous but the time, money and influence to satisfy them are limited."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economics is best defined as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The study of allocation of resources to satisfy human wants","The study of human behaviour in the process of buying and selling","Study of how nations  grow and improve their welfare","The study of how to allocate scarce resources to satisfy human wants"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economics may be described as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The study of demand and supply of things in our  environment","The study of production and distribution","The study of human behaviour in the allocation of scarce resources","The study of the employment of labour, capital, land and capital"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>From an economics point of view, an activity does not have cost when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Someone else pays for it","The returns are greater than costs","The choice involves given up nothing","Government pays for it"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Opportunity cost is a term which describes<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Initial cost of setting up a business venture","A study of the ways man devices to satisfy his unlimited wants from limited resources","Cost of one product in terms of forgone production of others","The mandatory equivalent of the utility of a commodity"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Scarcity in economics means<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A period of scarce things","When things are costly to acquire","Monopolisation of available resources by a few","None of the above."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these is the real cost of satisfying any want in the sense of the alternative that&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>has&nbsp; to be forgone<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Variable cost","Opportunity cost","Total cost","Prime cost"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economic analyses and conclusions can be divided into<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Consumption and production","Positive and normative","Microeconomics and macroeconomics","Demand and supply"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is NOT a measure of central tendency?&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Mean","Median","Average","Standard deviation"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is NOT a measure of dispersion<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Standard deviation","Mean deviation","Variance","Mean"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A normal good with close substitutes is likely to have its price elasticity of demand&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Between zero and one","Equal to unity","Greater than unity","Less than unity"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Demand for a factor of production is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A composite demand","A joint demand","A derived demand","An elasticity of demand"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given Demand function: Qd = 5P + 10; Supply function: Qs = 7P &ndash; 5. If the price is at N 5, the&nbsp;excess demand is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["35","30","10","5"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>If an increase in the price of a commodity leads to an increase in total revenue, then it&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>follows that the demand for the commodity is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Normal","Elastic","Inelastic","Abnormal"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>If the price of a commodity rises, the quantity demanded of the commodity remains the&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>same, then the demand for the commodity is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Static","Infinitely elastic","Externally determined","Perfectly inelastic"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The impact of a change in the price of commodity A on the quantity demanded of&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>commodity B is best explained using the concept of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Price-elasticity of demand","Cross-price elasticity of demand","Income elasticity of demand","Elasticity of substitution"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The change that is due to a movement from one supply curve to another along the same&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>price is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Change in supply","Change in quantity supplied","Elasticity change","Control price effect"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>When the supply of a commodity is fixed, its price elasticity of supply is said to be<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Perfectly elastic","Perfectly inelastic","Undefined","Elastic"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given Demand function: Q<sub>d<\/sub> = 5P + 10; Supply function: Q<sub>s<\/sub> = 7P &ndash; 5. The equilibrium&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>quantity is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["50","55","75.5","47.5"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the operation of market forces, the market is in equilibrium at the point where&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Demand and supply curve intersects in more than one point","The excess in the market can be conveniently stored","Excess demand is positive","Demand and supply curves intersect"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The basic feature of a market economy is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The reduction in the power of sellers","The enthronement of consumer sovereignty","The dismantling of barriers to trade","The perfectly elastic price for every transaction"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The following are the conditions that must be fulfilled for price determination EXCEPT<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Market merger","Market segmentation","Demand elasticities","Product differentiation"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The main function of price mechanism is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Limit consumer demand","Enable producers make profits","Allocate scarce resources among competing ends","Ensure consumer sovereignty"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A firm achieves least cost in production by substituting factors until<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Their factor prices are equal","Their marginal products are equal to the factor prices","Their marginal products are each equal to zero","The ratios of their marginal product equals the ratio of their prices"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A production possibility curve shows<\/strong><\/p>","options":["How much of resources a society uses to produce a particular commodity","The rate of inflation","The rate of unemployment in an economy","The various combinations of the commodities that can be produced"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A rightward shift in the production possibility frontier may be due to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Use of inferior inputs","Inefficiency","Improvement in production techniques and practices","Changes in the product mix"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Direct payment incurred for producing a commodity is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Implicit cost","Real cost","Opportunity cost","Explicit cost"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Diseconomies of scale can be caused by the following EXCEPT<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Managerial inefficiency","Increased resource-cost","Large market","Inefficient business environment"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Diseconomies of scale operates when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Doubling inputs brings about more than proportionate increase in output","Doubling inputs leads to a doubling of output","Doubling input brings about less than proportionate increase in output","Decrease in profit"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economic efficiency means<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Obtaining maximum output from available resources","Equitable distribution of nation\u0092s resources","Carrying out production without any waste","Producing the maximum output from available resources at the lowest possible cost"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>External economies are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The advantages accruing to firm as a result of its expansion","The advantages accruing to one firm as a result of the existence of other firms in the same locality","Benefits derived by a firm as a result of its own external economies policy","Economies reaped only by firms that are externally focused"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In economics, production is complete when&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Goods are produced in the factories","Goods are sold to the wholesaler","Goods and services are produced by the","Goods and services reach the consumer"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the study of economics, land, labour, capital and entrepreneur are referred to as&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>factors of production. These factors produce commodities only if they are __________<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Profitable to the production process","Purchased for the purpose of production","Combined in the production process","Produced adequately for the production process"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Production that takes place within the production possibility curve is said to be<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Inefficient","Possible","With increased output","X-efficient"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The act of combining factor inputs in order to obtain specific output is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Factor procurement","Manufacturing","Investment","Production"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The amount of labour a producer hires relative to other factor input depends on the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Price of labour or its wage","Price of labour, machinery and other inputs","Price of machinery","Price of other inputs"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The concept of economic efficiency primarily refers to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Obtaining the maximum output from available resources at the lowest possible cost","Conservation of our petroleum resources","Equity in the distribution of the nation\u0092s wealth","Producing without waste"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The law of diminishing returns often operates in the ________<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Long run","Short run","Medium term","Small scale production"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The main economic objective behind the production of goods and services in an economy&nbsp;is to&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Maximise profits","Satisfy human wants","Become self-reliant","Create job opportunities"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The residual of production which accrues to the ownership of land after all other expenses have been met is called<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Wages","Profit","Rent","Interest"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Average fixed cost is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Average total cost less the sum of average variable cost","Half the sum of all costs","Total fixed cost divided by the level of output","Total fixed cost plus marginal cost"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Average fixed cost is a rectangular hyperbola<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Since unit cost increases as output increases","Unit cost increases as output decreases","Unit cost decreases as output increases","Unit cost remains the same as output increases"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Long run cost is U-shaped because of the operation of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Economies of scale on the left hand side and diseconomies of scale on the right hand side","Diseconomies of scale on the left and right hand sides","Economies of scale on the left and right hand sides","Constant return to scale"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Marginal cost is the cost<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The lowest cost of producing goods","The cost of production of the most efficient firm in an industry","The cost of production of the most inefficient firm in an industry","The cost of production of the last unit of goods produced by a firm"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is NOT part of the fixed cost of a firm<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Interest on loans","Rent on buildings","Depreciation reserves","Wages"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is used to describe a payment representing a surplus in excess&nbsp; of&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>transfer earnings?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Interest rates","Opportunity costs","Economic rent","Indirect costs"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A perfectly competitive firm produces the most profitable output where its<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Marginal revenue equals average cost","Price equals average cost","Price equals marginal cost","Marginal cost equals marginal revenue"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Advertising is the main technique used for effecting in a monopolistic competition&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Market segmentation","Product differentiation","Price","Profit"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Output of a monopolist is usually determined at a point where<\/strong><\/p>","options":["P=MC","MR=MC","AR=AC","Marginal cost is rising"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Product homogeneity is one of the characteristics of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Perfect competition","Monopoly","Monopolistic competition","Oligopoly"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is compatible with a firm in a purely competitive market?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Demand is inelastic","Demand is infinitely elastic","Marginal cost is falling","Price is greater than marginal cost"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The difference between gross national product and net national product is equal to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Gross investment","Net investment","Net foreign income","Capital depreciation"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The difference between the Gross Domestic Product and the Gross National Product is the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Allowance for total depreciation","Total interest payments","Total tax and interest payments","Net income from abroad"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The multiplier is defined as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The ratio of the change in income to the change in investment","The change in investment divided by the change in income","1\/(MPC)","1\/(1-MPS)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A decrease in aggregate spending in an economy will ultimately lead to&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Boom","Deflation","Inflation","Recession"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Money serves well as a store of value in an environment devoid of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Unemployment","Bank robbery","Development-oriented central\/reserve bank","Inflationary pressure"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A document that shows the details of government revenue and expenditure in a year is&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Budget","Development plan","Rolling plan","Perspective plan"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The basic fiscal relation that exists among the three tiers of government in Nigeria is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["National budget appropriation","State-Local Government joint account","Revenue allocation from the federation account","Federal road projects"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The biggest source of government revenue in Nigeria is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Mining rents and royalties","Company income tax","Import duties","Petroleum profits tax"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A major obstacle to economic development is&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p>&nbsp;<\/p>","options":["A rise in industrial output","Low farm productivity","Free trade","Ineffective trade unions"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A sustained increase in the per capita income of a country over a period of time is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Economic growth","Economic development","Structural change","Stagflation"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In recent years, Nigerian economy has been registering a spectacular growth in ________Sector in the last ten years.<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Agriculture","Education","Telecommunication","Transport"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Nigeria, being a developing African country in the sub-Sahara, has put together a development blue-print called Vision 20:2020 which can ensure that the country becomes<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["One of the 20 developed countries by the year 2020","An African economic \u0091Tiger\u0092 by the year 2020","One of the 20 largest economies in the world by the year 2020","One of the 20 largest economies in sub-Saharan Africa by the year 2020 the 20 largest economies in the developing world by the year 2020"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is the standard concept of measuring and analyzing population&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>growth?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The rate of natural increase","The net migration rate","The rate of population increase","All of the above"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A major liability of a commercial bank arise from<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Customers deposits","Loans and advances","Overdrafts","Staff allowances"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Retailers in an economy perform the function of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Production","Exchange","Distribution","Investment"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The meaning of wage-price spiral is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Demand pull and cost push inflation pulling each other in different","Demand pull and cost push intensifying each other","That wages and price are rising at a proportional rate","That demand pull and cost push inflation increase employment"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following enterprise does not pursue the<\/strong><br \/><strong>sole objective of profit maximization<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Roads Nig Ltd","Union bank of Nigeria Ltd","Power holding & company of Nigeria","Kingsway Nigeria Ltd"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Palm oil industry is located in Edo state because the<\/strong><br \/><strong>state<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Imports raw material for oil industry","Is a palm tree growing area","Government does not engage land for other crops","Land is suitable for oil"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Disequilibrium in the balance of payments means<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Imports of the country exceeding its export","Deficit in the trade balance","Capital flowing out of the country exceeds the capital flowing into the country","Overall deficit or surplus in the current account and capital account of the balance of payment."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Full employment is a situation in which<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Every adult is employed","All adult who can work are employed","Only the disable are not employed","All those who are able and eligible to work can find employment"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>PHCN as a public corporation is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Duopoly","A power-generating industry in Nigeria","A monopoly","A mono polistically competitive industry"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Demand for a factor of production is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A composite demand","A joint demand","A derived demand","An elasticity demand"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Differential product is the characteristic feature of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Perfect competition","Pure competition","Monopoly","Monopolistic competition"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The channel for food distribution in Nigeria consists of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Producers wholesalers and retailers","Producers and consumers","producers and processor","Farmers processors and consumers"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>&nbsp;One disadvantage of sole proprietorships is its<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Limited liability","High profits","High sense of ownership","Low credit rating"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>For two substitute goods, the cross elasticity of<\/strong><br \/><strong>demand is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Greater than one but less than two","Zero","Negative","Positive"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is NOT a determinant of the<\/strong><br \/><strong>size of economically active population<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Age structure","Occupation of workers","Proportion of men to women","Efficiency of labour force"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The economic goal of public utilities is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Maximize profit","Expand assets","Minimize cost","Provide essential services"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The most important characteristic of money is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Portability","Intrinsic value","Acceptability","Usefulness"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is not a feature of economic<\/strong><br \/><strong>under development of a country?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Large number of high income earners relative to the population","High annual income for the few","High incidence of poverty","High infant mortality rate"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given the present state of the Nigerian economy<\/strong><br \/><strong>which of the following measurers will promote a more<\/strong><br \/><strong>rapid economic development<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Complete dependence on oil exports","Concentration on agricultural exports","Diversification of the economy","Introduction of nuclear energy in Nigeria"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The following except ONE, are the differences<\/strong><br \/><strong>between international trade and internal trade<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Differences in currency","Government control","Mobility of factors of production","Exchange of goods and services"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The central bank instrument of control does NOT<\/strong><br \/><strong>include<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Open market operations","Moral suction","Selective credit control","Printing banknotes"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The basic principle of co-operative societies are those<\/strong><br \/><strong>of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Workers ownership and worker control","Sole proprietorship","Partnership","Denying of credit facilities to members"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Generally property taxes<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Are borne entirely by landlords","Cannot be shifted in the long run","Are borne only by renters","Are born by all (renter, owner-occupiers and landlords)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The population level that yields the maximum output<\/strong><br \/><strong>when combined with available resources is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Dependent population","Maximum population","Active population","Optimum population"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Retailers in an economy perform the function of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Production","Exchange","Distribution","Investment"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>In a sole proprietorships the decision are made by the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Government","Board of directors","Owner","Shareholders"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The meaning of wage-price spiral is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Demand pull and cost push inflation pulling each other in different","Demand pull and cost push intensifying each other","That wages and price are rising at a proportional rate","That demand pull and cost push inflation increase employment"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following enterprise does not pursue the<\/strong><br \/><strong>sole objective of profit maximization?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Roads Nig Ltd","Union bank of Nigeria Ltd","Power holding & company of Nigeria","Kingsway Nigeria Ltd"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Palm oil industry is located in Edo state because the<\/strong><br \/><strong>state<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Imports raw material for oil industry","Is a palm tree growing area","Government does not engage land for other crops","Land is suitable for oil"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Disequilibrium in the balance of payments means<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Imports of the country exceeding its export","Deficit in the trade balance","Capital flowing out of the country exceeds the capital flowing into the country","Overall deficit or surplus in the current account and capital account of the balance of payment"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Full employment is a situation in which<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Every adult is employed","All adult who can work are employed","Only the disable are not employed","All those who are able and eligible to work can find employment"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>PHCN as a public corporation is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Duopoly","A power-generating industry in Nigeria","A monopoly","A monopolistically competitive industry"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Demand for a factor of production is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A composite demand","A joint demand","A derived demand","An elasticity demand"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Differential product is the characteristic feature of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Perfect competition","Pure competition","Monopoly","Monopolistic competition"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The channel for food distribution in Nigeria consists of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Producers wholesalers and retailers","Producers and consumers","Producers and processor","Farmers processors and consumers"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>One disadvantage of sole proprietorships is its<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Limited liability","High profits","High sense of ownership","Low credit rating"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>For two substitute goods, the cross elasticity of<\/strong><br \/><strong>demand is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Greater than one but less than two","Zero","Negative","Positive"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is NOT a determinant of the<\/strong><br \/><strong>size of economically active population<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Age structure","Occupation of workers","Proportion of men to women","Efficiency of labour force"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The economic goal of public utilities is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Maximize profit","Expand assets","Minimize cost","Provide essential services"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The most important characteristic of money is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Portability","Intrinsic value","Acceptability","Usefulness"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is not a feature of economic<\/strong><br \/><strong>under development of a country?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Large number of high income earners relative to the population","High annual income for the few","High incidence of poverty","High infant mortality rate"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given the present state of the Nigerian economy<\/strong><br \/><strong>which of the following measurers will promote a more<\/strong><br \/><strong>rapid economic development<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Complete dependence on oil exports","Concentration on agricultural exports","Diversification of the economy","Introduction of nuclear energy in Nigeria"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The following except ONE, are the differences<\/strong><br \/><strong>between international trade and internal trade<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Differences in currency","Government control","Mobility of factors of production","Exchange of goods and services"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The central bank instrument of control does NOT<\/strong><br \/><strong>include<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Open market operations","Moral suction","Selective credit control","Printing"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The basic principle of co-operative societies are those<\/strong><br \/><strong>of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Workers ownership and worker control","Sole proprietorship","Partnership","Denying of credit facilities to members"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Generally property taxes<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Are borne entirely by landlords","Cannot be shifted in the long run","Are borne only by renters","Are born by all (renter, owner-occupiers and landlords)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The population level that yields the maximum output<\/strong><br \/><strong>when combined with available resources is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Dependent population","Maximum population","Active population","Optimum population"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"}]